Finding Aid for the CLUE Records LSC.2441
UCLA Library Special Collections
CLUE records
1997-2016
UCLA Library Special Collections
Clergy and Laity United for Economic Justice (CLUE)
LSC.2441
11.3 linear feet (27 document boxes)
6 linear feet (6 unprocessed optical discs)
Clergy and Laity United for Economic Justice (CLUE) educates, organizes, and mobilizes faith leaders and community members to accompany workers in their struggle for good jobs, dignity, and justice. It is an independent organization of faith leaders in Los Angeles. The CLUE records were created and used by the CLUE organization and document the organization's activities. Collection materials include project/campaign binders, photographs, and materials from various local faith leaders.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email AskLSC@library.ucla.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of CLUE, 2023.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9997062238506533
Administrative History
Clergy and Laity United for Economic Justice educates, organizes, and mobilizes faith leaders and community members to accompany workers in their struggle for good jobs, dignity, and justice. It is an independent organization of faith leaders in Los Angeles, with origins in the late 1990s but goes back longer as part of the labor/religion alliance in the 1980s.
Scope and Content
Clergy and Laity United for Economic Justice (CLUE) records date from 1997 to 2016. The materials in this collection were created and used by the CLUE organization and document the organization's activities. Documented activities include projects/campaigns such as L.A. Worker Retention Law for city contractors at LAX; L.A. Living Wage for city contractors; Justice for Janitors; Respect at LAX coordinated campaign involving Local Unite Here 814, Service Employees International Untion (SEIU) Justice for Janitors, LA County Federation of Labor, CLUE; Security Officers United in Los Angeles (SOULA) Security Guards Campaign with SEIU, Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (LAANE) and CLUE; Car Wash Campaign focusing on wage theft, low wages, dangerous conditions and environmental concerns with Steelworkers Union, CLUE, and the Labor Center at Bonus Carwash in Santa Monica. Materials include project/campaign binders and photographs. The collection also contains materials from various local faith leaders such as Reverend Dick Gillete, Reverend James Lawson, and Rabbi Leonard Beerman.
Arrangement
The original arrangement of materials created by CLUE was retained.
Labor unions; Clergy; Labor movement; Working Class; Clergy and Laity United for Economic Justice (CLUE); Clergy and Laity United for Economic Justice (CLUE) -- Archives
- Young Religious Leaders Fellowship (YRLF) project training manual, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Binder of Faith Rooted Organizing (FRO) training curriculum, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Forging the Flame of Justice National Conference, June 19-21 Chicago, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Interfaith Worker Justice (IWJ) summer internship, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Binder from October, CLUE California inaugural state-wide conference in San Francisco (when CLUE merged with other Interfaith worker justice groups to form CLUE California), 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- National Interfaith Committee for Worker Justice May, 2003 and 2005 conference, Washington, DC Conference packet and resources, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Faith Rooted Organizing training binder, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Elizabeth Russell binder of Food Service 2012 Pomona College, California Lutheran Univ, Univ of La Verne (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes monthly reports, outline of her outreach targets and her speeches, letters of commitment from religious figures.
- Elizabeth Russell binder of 2011 monthly reports on LAX committee, Pomona Food Service, "the church", food justice action plan, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Training materials and essays used by Interfaith Worker Justice groups around the country, 2005-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes reports by Anjel F, intern, on one-to-one recruitment visits. Background essays on interfaith worker organizing.
- News coverage of CLUE campaigns on nursing homes, Santa Monica hotels, the church and worker justice, etc., undated (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  Includes clippings, magazines, and statements.
- "LAX Committee" end of the year report, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Grocery Workers Pilgrimage, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Interfaith Worker Justice (IWJ) affiliate handbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Summer Internships Orientation Week June 8-13, run by Interfaith Worker Justice, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Includes week's schedule and background materials plus lists of participants.
- "Food Service Workers Rock" - strategy materials related to food service providers, LAANE research, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "California Budget Training 101" - from Working Partnerships USA, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "Summer Internistas" packet, etc., 2009, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Includes materials from the Young Religious Leaders Summer Internship Program 2009, "What the Heck is Social Justice?", schedules, readings, and published materials.
- "Pomona College 2011" end of year report (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Includes organizer report, monthly reports ("Elizabeth Russell"), action plan, committee meetings, correspondence, and a press release.
- Food service - Elizabeth Russell (Cal Lutheran campaign), 2012 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "CLUE LA BOARD", 2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Published reports - LAANE, UCLA, Blue Ribbon Commissions, Prosper LA, Public Interest Projects, etc., 2007-2010 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
- CLUE West LA Committee meetings binder, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Santa Monica - Erin Tamayo binder, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Long Beach campaigns, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Teamsters Organizing Conference, 2009-2013 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
- Long Beach organizing, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- LAX/Inglewood Committee reports, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Binder: Santa Monica monthly reports, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
- Walmart campaign, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Food service - Elizabeth Russell binder, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- YRLF binder of documents and articles, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Signage for demonstrations and public hearings, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Liturgies including posada, stations of the cross, fasting, worker liturgies for breaking the fast, 1998 Interfaith Beverly Hills Procession (liturgy, photos, press coverage), 1998-2012 (Box 5, Folder 4-11)
- Resource information on transnationalism, the new economy, Walmart, the roots of economic inequality, rise of labor, guest workers and globalization., 2003-2008 (Box 5, Folder 12-19)
- Resources on labor law, including "Unfair Advantage" by Lance Copa on UN labor standards, 2000-2005 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
- Actions including songs, planning, how to get a permit, photos, Century Blvd Civil Disobedience, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 4-7)
- Readings for training, 2005-2007 (Box 6, Folder 8-12)
- Interfaith organizing articles and information, undated (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
- Media training materials and SPIN contacts, 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 15-16, Box 7, Folder 6)
- Organizer training exercises, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 17-19)
- Organizing strategies, 2001-2005 (Box 6, Folder 20-27)
- Trainings for youth on race, etc., 2002-2007 (Box 6, Folder 28-33)
- CLUE organizing model, undated (Box 6, Folder 34-37)
- Interfaith organizing, 2005-2011 (Box 6, Folder 38-40, Box 7, Folder 1-5, 7-8)
- Certificate of Special Congressional Recognition for Methodist Bishop Minerva Carcano, 2016 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- CLUE Los Angeles board notes and agendas, 2006-2014 (Box 7, Folder 10-14)
- Binder: "Catholic Research", 2009-2014 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  Includes Pasadena for a Living Wage campaign materials.
- CLUE CA materials, 2004-2011 (Box 7, Folder 16-18, Box 8, Folder 1-5)
  Includes statewide organization 2006-2011 documents, board meeting agendas/minutes, budget reports, lawsuit information re: Windsor Healthcare, board retreat information, 2008 Moral Budget Campaign.
- Binder: meetings, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  Includes New Sanctuary Movement (NSM)
- "Summary/Info. Living Wage ordinance, Copy of Living Wage ordinance, copy of Service Worker Retention Ordinance, Copy of Regulations, Articles about Living Wage Ordinance", 2007 (Box 8, Folder 7, Box 9, Folder 3)
- Hotel campaign information, 2004-2011 (Box 8, Folder 8-14)
- UFW file press clippings, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
- "Adams/La Brea Project", 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  Includes corporate research on developers, campaign strategy, copy of survey of residents, survey of displaced businesses, mapping demographics, workplan.
- Justice for Janitors - "Rising Out of Poverty For Just a Penny" - outline of campaign (with major talking points), clippings, flyers, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- "Board and Staff Meetings" - board meeting minutes staff reports - staff meeting minutes, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- "Living Wage Santa Monica", 2001-2003 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  Includes "To Fulfill The Dream: And End to Poverty for Workers - A Declaration of Conscience from the Religious Community in Los Angeles".
- Binder: meetings, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  Includes documentation from board meetings "Events" - Community Vigil in Sylmar, Press conference at Loews SM (Neil Comess-Daniels' speech), Wyndham/Radisson LAX speeches/readings, "Money, Deception, and Democracy" (in Santa Monica Living Wage campaign) 2003; SEDER Haggadah - 2 flyers (Temple Judea in Tarzana, First Methodist Church SM); "Interfaith Service of Blessing for the Immigrant Worker Freedom Riders" (play by play of speakers/program); Coalition for a better Inglewood, :"Staff Meetings" - Tasks and Timelines for Seders, newsletters.
- Binder (unlabeled, light blue): "Economic Justice How-To Manual: A Guide to Economic Justice Ministries for Use by Episcopal Congregations" - produced by the Episcopal Network for Economic Justice, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Binder: "Immigration-AFL/CIO", 2000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Assemblage of materials with index up front. Bulk of material related to "Latino and Immigrant Fairness Act of 2000".
- Small Binder: living wage campaign, 1997-2002 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Small binder: food service - CST and Cal Lutheran, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Large Binder: food service campaign, 2012-2013 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- "Las Vegas", 2004-2013 (Box 10, Folder 5-13)
  Includes clergy organizing, "Las Ramblas" planning - Stations Casino - Hyatt, civil disobedience training 2011 - Las Vegas fast, culinary organizing.
- 99 Cent Store campaign, 2004-2005 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Grocery and meat packing conditions, 2004-2012 (Box 11, Folder 1-10)
  Includes Vernon/Mapping - 2011 grocery contract fight - Adopt a Store and Pilgrimage - most 2010-2012 - TESCO - Fresh & Easy Campaign.
- Democracy Distorted Truth Commission re SM Living Wage ballot campaign, 2002-2003 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Santa Monica Hotel development, 2013 (Box 11, Folder 12-13)
  Includes monthly reports.
- Neighborhood mapping/research, 2004-2011 (Box 11, Folder 14-17, 19-20)
  Includes Santa Monica, East LA, South LA, Venice and Robertson areas.
- Outreach and mapping, 2010-2011 (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Internship materials, 2002-2012 (Box 11, Folder 21-23, Box 12, Folder 1-7)
  Workplan for intern Natasha one-on-one reports, intern training materials and flyers, Directed Study information.
- Interfaith materials, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 8-9)
  Includes folder "labor training".
- Grant writing proposal tools, 2002-2003 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Hotel Workers Rising, 2007-2008 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- IWJ Leadership Summit, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 12-13)
- Young Religious Leader program and fellowships, 2005-2013 (Box 12, Folder 14-17)
- FedEx campaign, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 18-19)
- Security workers campaign, 2004-2007 (Box 12, Folder 20-21, Box 13, Folder 1)
- Toyota UAW, 2010 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- David and Goliath general info, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Palm Springs Indian Casinos, 2007 (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
- Binder: Fresh & Easy campaign, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- TESCO, 2008-2012 (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
- Walmart - chaplain's program to Walmart workers, 2012 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- "PORT campaign", 2006-2007 (Box 13, Folder 10-11)
- Training materials, 2003-2006 (Box 13, Folder 14-15)
- RITZ Carlton, Pasadena, 2007 (Box 13, Folder 15)
- New Sanctuary Movement - immigration events and press, 2007-2012; 1 born-digital carriers (1 unprocessed optical disc) (Box 13, Folder 16, Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email AskLSC@library.ucla.edu.
- Wyndham Radisson/Labor in the Pulpit, 2000-2005 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- SM Hotel development, 2011-2012 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- SM Living Wage Propositions, 2000-2014 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- SM Displaced Workers Ordinance, 2001-2002 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- SM St John's Hospital campaign priorities, 2008-2009 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
- Binder: Mid-Wilshire CLUE Committee, 2008 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Binder: CLUE press coverage, 1997-2006 (Box 14, Folder 11-12)
- Coalition for Clean + Safe Ports - resources and materials, 2009 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Ports campaign, 2013 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Binder: "Carwash Campaign", 2011-2012 (Box 15, Folder 3-6)
  Inlcudes meeting minutes and reports.
- Binder: "Carwasheroes", 2010 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
- Binder: Hospitality Campaign, Long Beach, 2009-2013 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Black and Brown Leaders Committee, 2007-2014 (Box 16, Folder 4-5)
- Domestic Workers Bill of Rights, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Unite Here merger and dissolution, 2009 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- CLUE employee handbook, 2010 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Faith Rooted Organizing and religious traditions on workers' rights, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Organizing and movement building, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  Includes Cesar Chavez article.
- Economic Justice/Interfaith Workers Justice, 2007-2012 (Box 16, Folder 11-12)
- CLUE campaigns - hotel, grocery, food justice, 2008-2012 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Moral budget organizing, 2008 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Worker chaplaincy, 2011 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Is There a Women's Way of Organizing?, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Labor in the pulpit, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
- General CLUE materials, 2003-2007 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  Includes draft 2005 concept paper on key role of faith in justice work.
- Resources for a fair economy, 2006-2009 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  Includes reports, studies, and concept papers.
- Grocery workers, 2006-2010; 1 born-digital carriers (1 unprocessed optical disc) (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Security guards, 2005-2008; 2 born-digital carriers (2 unprocessed optical discs) (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
- Hotels Century Blvd, 2007-2013 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  Includes hotel contract.
- Airport service workers, 2008-2009 (Box 18, Folder 8)
- FedEx campaign, 2008-2009 (Box 18, Folder 9)
- "Black-Brown" project, 2007-2014 (Box 18, Folder 10-12)
  Includes 2008 African American and Latino breakfast and African-American - Hispanic Clergy/Community march for Peace April 29, 2010 and 2012.
- Binder: Clean Carwash, 2008-2010 (Box 18, Folder 13)
- Partnership documents including SEIU and Joint Labor Management Committee (JLMC), 2003-2008 (Box 18, Folder 14-15, Box 19, Folder 1-4)
- Research on CLUE, 2000-2002 (Box 19, Folder 5-7)
  USC Professor Pierrette Hondagneu-Sotelo's research on CLUE in the early 2000s for her book, God's Heart Has No Borders. Includes transcripts of interviews with several CLUE leaders at the time and field notes on CLUE events.
- Windsor Health Care nursing homes -- efforts to improve worker conditions, 2008-2009; 1 born-digital carriers (1 unprocessed optical disc) (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Faith Rooted Organizing trainings and outreach in Orange County, 2011-2012 (Box 19, Folder 9-11)
- Evangelicals and immigration reform, undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
- Immigrant rights work in Orange County, 2007-2013 (Box 19, Folder 13, Box 20, Folder 1-2)
- ACLU youth training on immigration rights, 2013 (Box 20, Folder 3, 8)
- Orange County CLUE Ingathering on Women and the Economy, 2015-2016 (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Education reform organizing in OC, 2008-2012; 1 born-digital carriers (1 unprocessed optical disc) (Box 20, Folder 5-7)
- Binder: Employee Free Choice Act, 2009 (Box 20, Folder 9)
- Binder: Port Truckers Campaign Long Beach, 2013 (Box 20, Folder 10)
- University of California Workers - AFSCME UC, 2008-2010 (Box 20, Folder 11)
- Minimum wage - 10 myths plus, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
- CLUE board of directors materials, 2013 (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Press clippings, 1998-2013 (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Pomona Food Service, 2012-2013 (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Organizers training agenda and materials, 2016 (Box 21, Folder 5)
- How labor unions organize, 2013-2014 (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Orange County Communities Organized for Responsible Development (OCCORD) in Orange County, undated (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Mid-Wilshire Hotel campaign, 2007 (Box 21, Folder 8)
- Binder: Mid-Wilshire Clue Committee 2007 Year at a Glance (Box 21, Folder 9)
- Binder: board retreat, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 10)
- Binder: current and emerging campaigns, 2008-2009 (Box 21, Folder 11)
- Clean Carwash, 2011 (Box 21, Folder 12-13)
- Grocery Store Workers Justice Pilgrimage clippings, 2003-2004 (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Anaheim Poverty Taskforce, 2011-2012 (Box 22, Folder 2)
- CLUE Orange County, 2010-2011 (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Santa Ana Building Healthy Communities Coalition, 2010-2015 (Box 22, Folder 4-5)
- Food service workers Loyola Marymount, 2010 (Box 22, Folder 6)
- CLUE Santa Monica Committee, 2012-2013 (Box 22, Folder 7)
- CLUE West LA Committee, 2010-2011 (Box 22, Folder 8)
- CLUE Long Beach, 2010-2013 (Box 22, Folder 9)
- Ironworkers and ironworker conditions, 2012 (Box 22, Folder 10-11)
- California Dream Act, 2010 (Box 22, Folder 12)
- SF Valley Committee, 2014 (Box 22, Folder 13)
- Immigration, 2009-2010 (Box 22, Folder 14)
- Bel-Aire Hotel, 2011-2013 (Box 22, Folder 15)
- A Declaration of Conscience from the Religious Community, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
- American Workers at the New Millennium report, 1999 (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Employee Free Choice Act information, 2007 (Box 23, Folder 3)
- Foundation grants, 2002-2011 (Box 23, Folder 4-13)
- LAX/CLUE LAX Committee meetings, 2006-2012 (Box 23, Folder 14-18)
- Prop 39, 2012 (Box 23, Folder 19)
- CLUE contacts business cards, undated (Box 23, Folder 20)
- Grocery worker information, 2004-2011 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- CLUE On Campus - board organizing document, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
- The New Sanctuary Movement articles, 2000-2008 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  Sojourners Magazine issue "The New Sanctuary Movement" (Sept-Oct, 2007); "Sacred Refuge" by Alexia Salvatierra.
- Immigration news clippings, 2006-2008 (Box 24, Folder 4-6)
- Immigration sanctuary pledges, 2006-2007 (Box 24, Folder 7, Box 25, Folder 6)
- New Sanctuary Movement National Conference, L.A., 2007 (Box 24, Folder 8)
- Immigration news clippings, 2006-2008 (Box 24, Folder 9, Box 25, Folder 1)
- New Sanctuary Movement Press, 2006-2007 (Box 24, Folder 10, Box 25, Folder 7)
- Immigration issues press, 2007-2008 (Box 24, Folder 11, Box 25, Folder 2, 4-5)
- Faith and immigrant rights, 2006-2007 (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Immigration/Sanctuary issue, 2006-2008 (Box 25, Folder 8)
- New Sanctuary Coalition agenda/minutes etc., 2007 (Box 25, Folder 9)
- Simi Valley Sanctuary controversy, 2007-2008 (Box 25, Folder 10)
- Long term care workers, 2010 (Box 25, Folder 11)
- Grocery workers, 2007-2011 (Box 25, Folder 12)
- Destination LA, 2011 (Box 25, Folder 13)
- Walmart campaign, 2005 (Box 25, Folder 14)
- Funding idea, 2005 (Box 25, Folder 15)
- CLUE Press Hotel Worker Support, 2001-2004 (Box 26, Folder 1)
- CLUE YRLF program funding, 2012 (Box 26, Folder 2)
- Reverend Lawson LA Times profile, 1998 (Box 26, Folder 3)
- Giants of Justice fundraising event programs, 2004-2013 (Box 26, Folder 4-5)
- Photographs, 2000-2014 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
  Photographs of CLUE 2004 Giants of Justice event, processionals, in gatherings, press conferences, etc. up to 2011. Some include names of those pictured written on the back. Additional photos of CLUE actions and other activities appear in the LAANE collection.